Irving Berlin Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Irving Berlin Collection 1895-1990 (bulk 1915-1990)
ML31.B48
Berlin, Irving, 1888-1989
750,000 items 915 containers 400 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Irving Berlin was an American lyricist and composer of over 1,200 songs. He was also a music publisher, theater owner, and a founding member of the American Society of Composers, Authors, and Publishers (ASCAP). The collection, which documents all aspects of his life and career, contains music scores, Berlin's handwritten and typewritten lyric sheets, publicity and promotional materials, personal and professional correspondence, photographs, business papers, legal and financial records, scrapbooks filled with press clippings, awards and honors, artwork and realia.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Berlin, Ellin--Correspondence.; Berlin, Ellin--Photographs.; Berlin, Ellin.; Berlin, Irving, 1888-1989--Archives.; Berlin, Irving, 1888-1989--Correspondence.; Berlin, Irving, 1888-1989--Manuscripts.; Berlin, Irving, 1888-1989--Photographs.; Berlin, Irving, 1888-1989.; Berlin, Irving, 1888-1989.; Berlin, Irving, 1888-1989. Selections.; Kresa, Helmy, 1904-1991.
Organizations
American Society of Composers, Authors and Publishers.; Irving Berlin Collection (Library of Congress); Irving Berlin Music Company.; Irving Berlin Music Company.; Irving Berlin, Inc.; Irving Berlin, Inc.; Music Box Theater (New York, N.Y.); Waterson, Berlin & Snyder Co.; Waterson, Berlin & Snyder Co.
Subjects
Composers--United States.; Motion picture music--Excerpts--Scores.; Music publishing--United States.; Music--Manuscripts--United States.; Musical films.; Musical theater--United States--20th century.; Musicals.; Popular music--United States.; Popular music--Writing and publishing--United States.; Songs--Texts.; Theater--United States.
Form/Genre
Artifacts (Object genre); Awards.; Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Photographic prints.; Programs (Documents); Promotional materials.; Scrapbooks.; Scripts (Documents)
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Mary Ellin Barrett, Linda Louise Emmet, and Elizabeth Irving Peters, 1992.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
Audiovisual materials have been transferred to the Library of Congress Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division. The sound recordings have been cataloged and can be identified as part of the "Irving Berlin Collection (Library of Congress)."
Access and Restrictions
The Irving Berlin Collection is open to research, though some items have restricted access. In addition, boxes bearing shelf numbers beginning with "B" or "L" are stored offsite. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Microfilm
The scrapbooks have been preserved on microfilm because of their fragile nature (Microfilm 92/20013 [MUS]).
Biographical Sketch
Date Event
1888, May 11 Born Israel Beilin to Moses Beilin and Leah Lipkin. One of eight children, his exact place of birth is unknown, although his family had been living in Tolochin, Byelorussia, (Russia)
1893 Beilin family immigrated to New York Family changed name to Baline
1901 Moses Baline died Izzy (Israel's nickname) quit school and left home to become a street singer
1905 Hired by songwriter-publisher Harry Von Tilzer to plug songs at Tony Pastor's Music Hall on 14th St., N.Y.
1906 Singing waiter at Mike Salter's Pelham Café, in Chinatown, N.Y. Began writing and performing his own lyrics and parodies
1907 Wrote lyrics for first published song, "Marie from Sunny Italy", and earned 37 cents in royalties Changed name to Irving Berlin
1908 Worked as a singing waiter at Jimmy Kelly's Wrote "The Best of Friends Must Part," the first song for which he composed both music and lyrics
1909 Hired by Ted Snyder Company, 112 W. 38th St., N.Y., as an in-house lyric writer Wrote "Dorando," his first song published by the Ted Snyder Company and first to achieve commercial success
1910 Wrote "Call Me Up Some Rainy Afternoon," his first number one selling song
1911 Dec. Became a partner with the Waterson, Berlin & Snyder publishing company, 112 W. 38th St., N.Y.
1911 First major international hit with "Alexander's Ragtime Band" Contributed four songs to the Ziegfeld Follies of 1911
1912 Feb. Married Dorothy Goetz, sister of songwriter E. Ray Goetz
1912 July Dorothy Berlin died of typhoid fever contracted in Cuba during their honeymoon
1912 Nov. Wrote "When I Lost You," his first important ballad
1914 Became a charter member of ASCAP Watch Your Step opened at the New Amsterdam Theatre, N.Y., his first score for the theater Waterson, Berlin & Snyder moved to the Strand Theatre Building at Broadway and 47th St., N.Y. Established Irving Berlin Inc., at 1571 Broadway, N.Y.
1918, Feb. 6 Became United States citizen
1918 Spring Entered the U.S. Army as a private
1918 Aug. Yip, Yip, Yaphank opened; Berlin wrote the Army show to raise money to build a service club at Camp Upton, N.Y. In the show he performed "Oh, How I Hate to Get Up In the Morning," and declined to include "God Bless America," (only to resurface 30 years later for the next World War effort)
1919 Honorably discharged from the Army Moved his offices to 1587 Broadway, N.Y. Wrote score for Ziegfeld Follies of 1919, including the hit "A Pretty Girl is Like a Melody"
1920 Built the Music Box Theatre on W. 45th St., N.Y., in partnership with Sam Harris
1921 Irving Berlin Inc. moved to 1607 Broadway, N.Y. Music Box Revue of 1921 opened at the Music Box Theatre, produced by partner Sam H. Harris
1922 Leah Baline (Irving's mother) died Music Box Revue of 1922 opened at the Music Box Theatre
1924 Met Ellin Mackay, daughter of Clarence Mackay, (owner of the postal telegraph company), and Katherine Duer Blake Wrote hits "All Alone" and "What'll I Do" Music Box Revue of 1924 opened, the fourth revue in his series at the Music Box Theatre
1925 Wrote "Always" and "Remember" The Cocoanuts opened in New York
1926, Jan. 4 Irving and Ellin married at City Hall accompanied by national press and against the wishes of her father; after an eight month honeymoon aboard the USS Leviathan, the couple returned to Manhattan
1926, Nov. 25 Daughter Mary Ellin Berlin born
1926 Dec. Wrote "Blue Skies" and on Christmas day presented it to his month old daughter, "for Mary Ellin, Christmas 1926"
1927 Ziegfeld Follies of 1927 opened, with complete score by Berlin Al Jolson sang "Blue Skies" in the first full-length soundtrack film, The Jazz Singer
1928, Dec. 1 Son Irving Berlin Jr. born (died 25 days later)
1928 The Cocoanuts opened in London Berlin wrote theme songs for the films The Awakening, Coquette, and Lady of the Pavement
1929 Wrote songs for the films Hallelujah, Mammy, including "Let Me Sing and I'm Happy," and Puttin' on the Ritz featuring the title song Film version of The Cocoanuts, shot in New York, was released
1930 Wrote the score for the film Reaching for the Moon. All but two songs were dropped due to the dying popularity of musicals
1932, Feb. 13 Face the Music opened in New York
1932, Feb. 21 Daughter Linda Louise Berlin born
1932 Songs "How Deep Is the Ocean" and "Say It Isn't So" were released
1933 Irving Berlin Inc. moved to 799 7th Ave., N.Y. As Thousands Cheer opened at Music Box Theatre; score included "Easter Parade," "Heat Wave," and "Supper Time"
1934 Appeared on cover of Time magazine
1935 New York premiere of film Top Hat, score included "Cheek to Cheek," "Isn't This a Lovely Day," and "Top Hat, White Tie and Tails"
1936, June 6 Daughter Elizabeth Irving Berlin born
1936 New York premiere of film Follow the Fleet, score included "I'm Putting All My Eggs in One Basket," "I'd Rather Lead a Band," and "Let's Face the Music and Dance"
1937 New York premiere of the film On the Avenue, score included "I've Got My Love to Keep Me Warm," and "Slumming on Park Avenue"
1938, Nov. 10 "God Bless America" introduced by Kate Smith on an Armistice Day radio broadcast
1938 Films Alexander's Ragtime Band and Carefree released
1939 Film Second Fiddle released
1940 Louisiana Purchase opened at the Imperial Theatre, N.Y.
1941 Film version of Louisiana Purchase released Wrote three songs for the war effort and donated the royalties to the following organizations: the American Red Cross ("Angels of Mercy"); the Treasury Department ("Any Bonds Today"); and the Ordinance Department ("Arms for the Love of America")
1942, July 4 This is the Army opened at the Broadway Theatre in New York; Berlin appeared in the show and sang "Oh! How I Hate to Get Up in the Morning"
1942 Aug. Film Holiday Inn premiered in New York; featured Bing Crosby's rendition of "White Christmas"
1942, Oct. 1 National tour of This is the Army opened at the National Theatre in Washington, D.C.
1943 Film version of This is the Army released, raising more than nine million dollars for Army Relief
1944 Berlin severed partnership with Saul Bornstein Irving Berlin Inc. closed Irving Berlin Music Company opened at 1650 Broadway, N.Y.
1945 This is the Army overseas tour ended Awarded the Medal of Merit by President Harry S. Truman
1946, May 16 Annie Get Your Gun opened at the Imperial Theatre, N.Y.
1946, Oct. 16 New York premiere of the film Blue Skies
1948, June 30 New York premiere of the film Easter Parade
1948 Dec. Traveled with Bob Hope to Germany to entertain American troops during the airlift
1949 Miss Liberty opened at the Imperial Theatre, N.Y.
1950 Film version of Annie Get Your Gun released Call Me Madam opened at the Imperial Theatre, N.Y.
1951 Received Tony Award for Call Me Madam score
1952 Began preliminary work on unproduced show Palm Beach, based on Cleveland Amory's book The Last Resorts
1953 Film version of Call Me Madam released
1954 Awarded the Congressional Medal of Honor by President Dwight D. Eisenhower Films White Christmas and There's No Business Like Show Business released
1955 Worked on unproduced show Sentimental Guy, based on The Legendary Mizners by Alva Johnston
1957 "Sayonara" was featured in the film of the same name
1962 Mr. President opened at the Imperial Theatre
1963 Began work on film project Say it with Music for MGM Irving Berlin Music Company moved to 1290 Avenue of the Americas, N.Y.
1966 Annie Get Your Gun revived at Lincoln Center, New York State Theater
1968 Honored with a television tribute by Ed Sullivan
1969 MGM stopped production of Say it with Music
1973 Last public appearance singing "God Bless America" at White House dinner honoring returning American prisoners of war from Vietnam
1977 Awarded the Medal of Freedom by President Gerald Ford
1986 One of twelve naturalized Americans awarded the Liberty Medal from President Ronald Reagan in celebration of the Statue of Liberty's hundredth anniversary
1988, May 11 ASCAP tribute at Carnegie Hall in celebration of Berlin's 100th birthday
1988, July 29 Ellin Berlin died
1988 Irving Berlin Music Company moved to 29 West 46th St., N.Y.
1989, Sept. 22 Died, New York City Flag flown over US Capitol in Berlin's honor
1990 June Irving Berlin Music Company moved to the Rodgers & Hammerstein Organization, 1633 Broadway, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The Irving Berlin Collection, spanning the years 1895-1990 with the bulk of the material dating from 1915-1990, documents the life and work of one of the twentieth century's most legendary American musical figures. While the collection provides a comprehensive record of Berlin's life as a composer, lyricist, publisher and theater owner, it also serves as a resource for the study of American popular music. Berlin wrote more than 1,200 songs, including such standards as "White Christmas," "There's No Business Like Show Business," and "God Bless America," that gave a musical voice to much of the American experience of the twentieth century. A large part of his reputation also justifiably rests on his great ballads of the 1920s and 1930s, including "Always," "Cheek to Cheek," "How Deep Is the Ocean (How High Is the Sky)," "Let's Face the Music and Dance," and "What'll I Do." The materials in the Irving Berlin Collection document additional aspects of Berlin's career, such as music publishing, theater ownership, and founding membership in the American Society of Composers, Authors, and Publishers. The breadth of his activity coupled with his longevity (he died at age 101) produced one of the largest collections in the custody of the Library of Congress Music Division.
The Show Music series consists of scores, sketches, lyric sheets, and scripts from Berlin's Broadway musicals and films, including Annie Get Your Gun, This is the Army, and Holiday Inn. Much of the material in the Non-Show Music series comes from Berlin's early career. Full scores, piano-vocal scores and sketches are in the hand of various musical secretaries, primarily that of longtime secretary Helmy Kresa (1905-1991). Manuscript lyric sheets are in the hand of Irving Berlin.
The Project Files series supplements the music with clippings, promotional material, correspondence, scripts, financial and legal documents, artwork and other materials from Berlin's musicals and films. The Subject Files series contains documents relating to various business interests, including ASCAP and Berlin's Music Box Theatre, and personal items relating to his family and private life.
The Scrapbooks are filled with press clippings and show-related materials that detail Berlin's personal as well as professional accomplishments.
The Correspondence series contains extensive personal and professional correspondence that documents Berlin's relationships with family, friends, colleagues, and musical and political public figures, as well as his role in ASCAP. The personal items include letters and cards sent between Irving and his wife Ellin, and correspondence with multiple family members, including Ellin's father, Clarence Mackay. The correspondence also includes fan mail and milestone birthday wishes.
The documents in the Legal Papers series pertain to the Irving Berlin Music Co., copyright assignments, legal cases, and permission documentation. The Financial Papers series includes personal bank statements and insurance documents, household bills and receipts, correspondence, donations and contributions, royalty statements, and investments. In addition, financial records are held for the Irving Berlin Charitable Fund, Irving Berlin Music Company, and Irving Berlin, Inc.
The Photographs series contains photographs of Berlin, his family, and colleagues in the music business.
The Awards and Tributes series contains numerous tributes awarded to Berlin, many given by ASCAP. The Original Artwork series includes photographed reproductions of original paintings, and the Realia series contains personal artifacts, such as the flag that flew over the Capitol on Berlin's 100th birthday, address books, notebooks, and calendars. The final series, Non-Berlin Materials, contains music, lyrics, and screenplays by other individuals.
Organization of the Irving Berlin Collection
The Irving Berlin Collection is organized into thirteen series:
Show Music
Non-Show Music
Project Files
Subject Files
Scrapbooks
Correspondence
Legal Papers
Financial Papers
Photographs
Awards and Tributes
Original Artwork
Realia
Non-Berlin Materials
http://lccn.loc.gov/2012562128
Container List
- Show Music (Box 1-219)
  - Alexander's ragtime band, (Film, 1938 ) (Box-folder 32-34)
    - Scores and parts (Box-folder 32-33)
      - Bound printed piano-vocal score; [173] p. (Box-folder 32/1)
      - Bound photocopy of copyist’s manuscript piano short scores; [188] p. (Box-folder 32/2)
      - Alexander's ragtime band
        - Manuscript guitar part; [1] p. (Box-folder 33/1)
        - Photocopies of copyist’s manuscript parts (Box-folder 33/1)
        - Sheet music (Box-folder 33/1)
      - Everybody step
        - Sheet music (Box-folder 33/2)
      - For your country and my country
        - Fair copy (Kresa) manuscript piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 33/3)
        - Photocopy of sheet music, No cover (Box-folder 33/3)
      - In my harem
        - Fair copy (Kresa) manuscript piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 33/4)
      - Lazy
        - Manuscript piano-vocal scores; [4], 4 p. (Box-folder 33/5)
        - Fair copy (Kresa) manuscript piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 33/5)
        - Sheet music (Box-folder 33/5)
      - Marching along with time
        - Photocopies of copyist’s manuscript piano-vocal score(2); 5 p. each (Box-folder 33/6)
        - Typescript lyric sheets; [4] leaves (Box-folder 33/6)
        - Photocopied parts (Box-folder 33/7)
      - Marie
        - Sketch; [1] p. (Box-folder 33/8)
        - Fair copy (Kresa) manuscript piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 33/8)
        - Sheet music (Box-folder 33/8)
      - My walking stick, Laid in: note to copyist
        - Manuscript piano-vocal score; [4] p. (Box-folder 33/9)
        - Sketch; [1] p. (Box-folder 33/9)
        - Fair copy (Kresa) manuscript piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 33/9)
        - Photocopies of manuscript piano-vocal score; 5 p. each, 2 copies (Box-folder 33/9)
        - Photocopies of manuscript lead sheet; [1] p. each, 2 copies (Box-folder 33/9)
        - Printed piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 33/9)
        - Typescript and carbon copy lyric sheets; [11] leaves (Box-folder 33/9)
      - Now it can be told
        - Manuscript piano-vocal score; [4] p. (Box-folder 33/10)
        - Manuscript piano score; [2] p., With annotations (Box-folder 33/10)
        - Manuscript lead sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 33/10)
        - Fair copy (Kresa) manuscript piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 33/10)
        - Photocopies of manuscript piano-vocal score; 5 p. each, 2 copies (Box-folder 33/10)
        - Holograph lyric sheets; [2] leaves (Box-folder 33/10)
        - Typescript lyric sheets; [4] leaves (Box-folder 33/10)
      - Oh! How I hate to get up in the morning
        - Sheet music (Box-folder 33/11)
      - Pack up your sins and go to the devil
        - Fair copy (Kresa) manuscript piano-vocal score; 6 p. (Box-folder 33/12)
      - Ragtime violin!, Alternate title: The ragtime violin
        - Fair copy (Kresa) manuscript piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 33/14)
      - Remember
        - Manuscript piano-vocal scores; 11 p. each, SATB, SSA, TTBB (Box-folder 33/15)
        - Typescript lyric sheet; [1] leaf (Box-folder 33/15)
        - Sheet music (Box-folder 33/15)
      - Say it with music
        - Manuscript guitar part; [1] p. (Box-folder 33/16)
      - Some sunny day
        - Fair copy (Kresa) manuscript piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 33/17)
      - That international rag, Alternate title: The international rag
        - Copyist’s manuscript piano-vocal score; 5 p. (Box-folder 33/18)
        - Photocopy of manuscript piano-vocal score; 5 p., With annotations (Box-folder 33/18)
        - Reverse photocopy of manuscript piano-vocal score; 5 p. (Box-folder 33/18)
      - When I lost you
        - Sheet music (Box-folder 33/19)
      - When the midnight choo-choo leaves for Alabam’, Alternate title: When that midnight choo, choo, leaves for Alabam
        - Fair copy (Kresa) manuscript piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 33/20)
    - Scripts (Box 34)
      - Typescript musical sequence and outline; [11] p. each, With carbon copy; At top: 3/19/42 (Box-folder 34/1)
      - Carbon copy typescript musical sequence and outline; [11] p. each, 2 copies; Laid in: Envelope from Twentieth Century-Fox Film Corporation; On cover: Alexander’s ragtime band 1st originals (Box-folder 34/1)
      - Typescript list of musical numbers; 2 p. (Box-folder 34/1)
      - Typescript story line; 93 p., On cover: Alexander’s ragtime band, 1st [sic] (Box-folder 34/2)
      - Carbon copy of typescript storyline and screenplay; 122 p., On cover: 2nd Alexander’s ragtime band (Box-folder 34/2)
      - Mimeograph copy of typed script; 153 p., On cover: shooting final, January 27, 1938 (Box-folder 34/3)
  - Annie get your gun, Stage, 1946; film, 1950; television, 1957; stage revival, 1966 (Box 1-5, 35-70)
    - Bound piano-vocal score; 153 p. (Box-folder 35/1)
    - Anything you can do
      - Full score #31; [36] p. (Box-folder 1/1)
      - Manuscript piano-vocal scores; 3 p., [1] p. (Box-folder 36/1)
      - Photocopy of copyist’s manuscript piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 36/1)
      - Fair copy (Kresa) manuscript piano-vocal score; 5 p. (Box-folder 36/1)
      - Manuscript and typescript lyric sheets; [28] leaves (Box-folder 36/1)
      - Parts Set A, #31 (Box-folder 38/1)
      - Parts Set B, #31 (Box-folder 43/1)
      - Parts Set B, alternate #31 (Box-folder 43/2)
    - Ceremonial chant
      - Full score #20; 10 p. (Box-folder 1/2)
      - Parts Set B, #20 (Box-folder 43/3)
      - Parts Set D, #20 (Box-folder 54/1)
    - Circus (dance)
      - Full score; [34] p. (Box-folder 1/3)
      - Parts Set A, #14 (Box-folder 38/2)
      - Parts Set B, #14 (Box-folder 43/4)
    - Colonel Buffalo Bill, Alternate title: Opening, Act I
      - Full score #2; 35 p. (Box-folder 1/4)
      - Full score, utility, #7; 6 p. (Box-folder 1/5)
      - Full score, utility, #12A; 6 p. (Box-folder 1/5)
      - Manuscript piano-vocal score; 7 p. (Box-folder 36/2)
      - Photocopy manuscript piano-vocal score; 6 p. (Box-folder 36/2)
      - Fair copy (Kresa) manuscript piano-vocal score; 7 p. (Box-folder 36/2)
      - Typescript lyric sheets; [7] leaves (Box-folder 36/2)
      - Parts Set A, utility (Box-folder 39/1)
      - Parts Set B, #2 (Box-folder 43/5)
      - Parts Set B, new #7 (Box-folder 44/1)
      - Parts Set B, utility 1A, #12A, #17 (Box-folder 44/2)
      - Parts Set D, entrance #7 (Box-folder 54/2)
      - Parts Set D, utility #1A, #12A, #17 (Box-folder 54/3)
    - Doin' what comes natur'lly
      - Full score #4; 15 p. (Box-folder 1/6)
      - Full score, Encore #4; 14 p. (Box-folder 1/7)
      - Manuscript piano-vocal score; 2 p., Laid in: manuscript vocal sketch; [1] p. (Box-folder 36/3)
      - Photocopy of manuscript piano-vocal score; 4 p. (Box-folder 36/3)
      - Printed piano-vocal score; 3 p. each, 3 copies (Box-folder 36/3)
      - Typescript lyric sheets; [47] leaves (Box-folder 36/3)
      - Sheet music (Box-folder 36/3)
      - Parts Set A, #4 (Box-folder 39/2)
      - Parts Set B, #4 (Box-folder 44/3)
      - Parts Set C, encore (Box-folder 51/1)
      - Parts Set C, opening scene #29B (Box-folder 51/2)
      - Parts Set D, #4 (Box-folder 54/4)
    - Entr'acte
      - Full score, Coda; 4 p. (Box-folder 1/8)
      - Full score, Ending; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/8)
      - Parts Set B, #22A (Box-folder 44/4)
      - Parts Set D, #22A, 23 (Box-folder 54/5)
    - Finale
      - Parts Set D, #33A (Box-folder 54/6)
    - Funeral march
      - Full score; 6 p. (Box-folder 1/9)
      - Parts Set C (Box-folder 51/3)
    - The girl that I marry
      - Full scores(2); 11 p. each (Box-folder 1/10)
      - Full scores #5; 11 p., 10 p. (Box-folder 1/10)
      - Full score, Ballroom scene #25; 12 p. (Box-folder 1/11)
      - Full score, Opening; 5 p. (Box-folder 1/12)
      - Full scores, Reprise #29; 10 p., 11 p. (Box-folder 1/13)
      - Full score, Waltz; p. 5-12 (Box-folder 1/14)
      - Full score-with "You can't get a man without a gun" #22; 14 p. (Box-folder 1/15)
      - Manuscript piano score; [2] p. (Box-folder 36/4)
      - Manuscript lead sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 36/4)
      - Photocopy of copyist's manuscript piano-vocal score; [2] p. (Box-folder 36/4)